Tim Weigel

timweigel@gmail.com https://www.timweigel.dev https://www.linkedin.com/in/timothyweigel/

Profile

I'm a skilled database administrator with database development experience. I'm enthusiastic, and a fast learner. I'm process-oriented, careful, methodical, and thorough. I ask questions when I need to, and my research skills are top-notch. I document my work. I'm an active part of the SQL Server community.

Experience

DIGITAL OUTREACH COORDINATOR (VOLUNTEER), HOUSTON COUNTY ALABAMA DEMOCRATIC PARTY; DOTHAN, AL – APRIL 2020 - PRESENT

- Developing a database solution for the Houston County Alabama Democratic Party.
 Conducted requirements analysis by interviewing key Party personnel and reviewing existing data sources. Identifying hosting providers compatible with budgetary requirements
- Manage access and security to Party technology resources on Google Drive, GMail, Facebook, and Twitter platforms
- Manage and conduct marketing and email campaigns via Mailchimp, and coordinate opt-in and opt-out information with Party membership rolls

SQL SERVER DBA, NATIONAL MULTIPLE SCLEROSIS SOCIETY; DENVER, CO (REMOTE) – MARCH 2018 - MAY 2020

- Assisted with planning and executing migration of internal CRM platform to Salesforce's Nonprofit Success pack, including assisting with vendor selection for Enterprise Service Bus platform
- Developed and implemented a bulk copy-based approach to importing data into staging environments resulting in runtime reduction from hours to minutes in comparison to prior script-based data load approach
- Developed change tracking functionality for integration processing including data modeling and architecture, stored procedures to extract desired changeset data from change tables and perform staging table cleanup, auditing functionality utilizing triggers, archive and purge processes, and SQL Server Agent jobs to coordinate the various functions.

- Conducted post-implementation development to extend integration functionality
 including refactoring inefficient T-SQL views and stored procedures, and developing
 and implementing new logic in the Dell Boomi iPaaS tool in coordination with the
 integration lead.
- Wrote the foundational documents of the cloud-first architecture plan to guide the Society's long-term data strategy. Advocated planned transitions from on-premises and laaS-based solutions to more scalable PaaS solutions for large-scale data storage, analytics, and data science, while recognizing platform gaps that require maintenance of traditional architecture for Master Data Management, 3rd-part SSIS tools, and SSRS functionality
- Managed Data Warehouse SQL Server environment in a hybrid Azure Infrastructure as a Service virtual machine/physical server environment, including production, QA, and development instances in a high-availability configuration utilizing Always On Availability Groups. Ensure maintenance and backup operations are successfully performed
- Supported SQL Server Integration Services integration and SQL Server Reporting Services reporting environments. Troubleshoot errors in concert with integration and reporting staff, identify root causes of database-layer issues, and manage security across environments
- Implemented performance monitoring improvements using Extended Events
- Participated in database release lifecycle, including managing deployments to QA and production environments as well as the scheduled refreshing of development and QA environments

SENIOR DATABASE ADMINISTRATOR, PGI; COLORADO SPRINGS, CO – NOVEMBER 2016 - MARCH 2018

- Began pilot program to migrate critical 24x7 systems to SQL Server 20014 from SQL Server 2008R2. Included planning SAN changes, heterogeneous cluster upgrades from Windows Server 2008R2 to Windows Server 2016, and determining optimal methods to move databases between legacy and new instances within time-constrained outage windows
- Conducted SAN consolidation operations on primary production and billing SQL Server instances, significantly reducing the number of LUNs required to conduct operations.

- Conducted comprehensive configuration review of all production database servers and provided recommendations and plans to bring noncompliant instances into line with best practices.
- Conducted review of Active Directory group membership and implemented plans to break up large groups in order to ensure appropriate user access to database resources.
- Built test Windows and SQL Server environment for Disaster Recovery environment utilizing SAN snapshot replication.
- Maintained production SQL Server environment, including managing maintenance operations, troubleshooting performance issues, and resolving production outages in a blended physical and Amazon Web Services Elastic Compute Cloud environment.
- Maintain and troubleshoot transactional replication to systems across the globe using Replication Monitor and T-SQL scripts.
- Support SQL Server failover clusters via Failover Cluster Manager, including installing cluster instances, rolling upgrades to cluster instances, and failing over SQL Server instances as needed to secondary cluster nodes.
- Implemented plan to ensure asynchronous Always On Availability Group failovers do not result in data loss.
- Mentored junior DBAs, helping them to plan work, expand their knowledge and technical skills, and develop into more rounded data professionals.

SQL SERVER DBA, NATIONAL MULTIPLE SCLEROSIS SOCIETY; DENVER, CO – MARCH 2016 - NOVEMBER 2016

- Managed Data Warehouse SQL Server environment in an Azure Virtual Machine environment, including production, QA, and development instances
- Standardized multiple SQL Server instances to bring in line with accepted best practices for management, including backups
- Managed Always On Availability Group, including configuring backups and SQL Server Agent jobs to run on the appropriate replica

- Worked closely with application developer to implement best practices for application and database code deployments
- Worked closely with reporting developers to improve reporting data transfer process and strategies
- Assisted Data Warehouse team with evaluating an MDS implementation proposal from a technical and operational perspective
- Assisted team to determine state of implementation at close of Data Warehouse UI vendor engagement
- Provided guidance and assistance to colleagues regarding SQL Server best practices
- Provided guidance and assistance to colleagues with T-SQL coding questions

SQL SERVER DBA, XTIVIA; COLORADO SPRINGS, CO – JULY 2015 - MARCH 2016

- Resolved data warehouse load performance issues for a large national retailer via implementing appropriate index maintenance strategies.
- Resolved and provided root-cause analysis of complex failure in a Change Data Capture configuration for a major retailer.
- Successfully recovered data from a corrupt 3 TB database for a major application hosting provider.
- Provided in-house training on Change Data Capture.
- Provide remote management and monitoring of diverse SQL Server environments for a wide range of clients ranging from large enterprises to small businesses.
- Configure and administer Analytics Platform Service Parallel Data Warehouse appliances
- Provide consulting and guidance for new SQL Server installations, upgrades, and ongoing maintenance according to best practices.
- Coordinate configuration, maintenance, and upgrades in hosted SQL Server environments with multiple hosting providers including Latisys, Hosting, and Rackspace.

- Conduct health checks on installed SQL Server instances to aid clients in optimizing their environments.
- Configure, troubleshoot and maintain a wide variety of data distribution infrastructures, including replication (transactional and snapshot), log shipping, and Always On Availability Groups.
- Install, configure, and support multiple SQL Server technologies including SQL Server Analysis Services, SQL Server Integration Services, and SQL Server Reporting Services.
- Provide support for production issues including performance issues, system outages, capacity issues, and database corruption.

Education

Colorado College, Colorado Springs, CO – BA Asian Studies, 2006

- Bachelor of Arts in Asian Studies (Cum Laude)
- Received Excellence in Asian Studies award
- Member Phi Beta Kappa β of Colorado

Skills

- SQL Server ecosystem administration, including
 - Backups, consistency checks, and index maintenance
 - SQL Server Integration Services and SQL Server Reporting Services management and troubleshooting
 - Database planning and architecture
 - High-availability and disaster recovery planning and implementation including clustering
 - Database replication
 - Performance monitoring and tuning

- Windows Server administration, both physical and Azure Virtual Machine
- Dell Boomi process development and maintenance
- Business process development
- Compliance audits

SQL Server Community Involvement

WIREGRASS SQL & DATA COMMUNITY; DOTHAN, AL – 2020

- Founded the Wiregrass SQL & Data Community in early 2020 to provide learning and networking opportunities to the underrepresented data community in the Wiregrass region encompassing Dothan, AL and surrounding counties.
- Secured PASS affiliation, meeting space through the Dothan Houston County Library System, set up social media accounts on Twitter, Facebook, and LinkedIn to conduct communication and marketing, and conducted marketing activities through various social media channels.

COLORADO SPRINGS SQL SERVER USERS GROUP; COLORADO SPRINGS, CO - 2016 - 2018

- Vice President of Membership from January 2017 to December 2018: Managed group membership and engaged in outreach activities to maintain and increase group membership.
- Vice President of Marketing from January 2016 to December 2016: Revived group's
 dormant Twitter and Facebook accounts and implemented a social media strategy to
 increase group engagement. Coordinated email communication with group members
 about upcoming events and community news. Collaborated with our sponsors to ensure
 their messages reached our membership, leading to several staffing agencies
 increasing their sponsorship of our group.
- Assisted with planning and running multiple SQL Saturday events. Repeatedly
 succeeded in increasing the number of sponsors for the events, bringing new sponsors
 on board for 2016 and 2017. Participated in speaker vetting and selection, and event
 schedule planning. Coordinated volunteer engagement, overseeing volunteer staff.
 Participated actively in event setup and teardown.

TALKS

Change Tracking Methods in SQL Server

- SQL Saturday Denver September 2018
- Denver SQL Server Users Group April 2018
- SQL Saturday Colorado Springs March 2018

TempDB Management

- Denver SQL Server Users Group April 2017
- Colorado Springs SQL Server Users Group February 2017

Change Data Capture

- MagicPASS (Remote, Orlando, FL) April 2017
- Colorado Springs SQL Server Users Group September 2015

Change Tracking

• Colorado Springs SQL Server Users Group – October 2016